<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A subtill practise, vvrought in Paris by Fryer Frauncis who to deceiue Fryer Donnet of a sweet skind nun which he secretly kept, procured him to go to Rome, where he tolde the Pope a notable lie concerning the taking of the king of France prisoner by the Duke de Mayne: for which, they whipt ech other so greeuously in Rome, that they died thereof within two dayes after.</title>
            <author>L. R., fl. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10299</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20582.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846093</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846093</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 339:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A subtill practise, vvrought in Paris by Fryer Frauncis who to deceiue Fryer Donnet of a sweet skind nun which he secretly kept, procured him to go to Rome, where he tolde the Pope a notable lie concerning the taking of the king of France prisoner by the Duke de Mayne: for which, they whipt ech other so greeuously in Rome, that they died thereof within two dayes after.</title>
                  <author>L. R., fl. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Adam Islip] for Thomas Nelson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: L.R.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 20582+ on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Friars --  France --  Humor --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11036:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:11036:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <p>A Subtill practiſe, vvrought in Paris by Fryer Frauncis, who to deceiue Fryer Donnet of a ſweet skind Nun which he ſecretly kept, procured him to go to <hi>Rome, where he tolde the Pope a notable lie concerning the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the king of France priſoner by the Duke de Mayne:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For which, they whipt ech other ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly in Rome, that they died thereof within two dayes after.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed for Thomas Nelſon.</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11036:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11036:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue at length (gentle coſen) obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſome leiſure to acquaint you with the condition of my welfare, which I aſſure you to be farre better, then the vſuall vncertainty of a traueller. For departing out of England vnder the right Honorable the Lord Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies protection, we happily arriued at Déepe in France within a little while after, whence marching vnto the frontiers of the enemy, we ſhared our fortunes in thoſe famous atchieuements that atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſtations of the inuincible <hi>Henry</hi> of Burbon, which hot purſuite of Honor once ſlackte, I tooke my way to Caen in Normandy, where I haue remained euer ſince, in what ſtate you may imagine by my old wonte, merry I thanke God, how euer the deuill now and then, ſomewhat youthfully diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed makes a dauncing ſchoole in the bottome of my purſe for a whole wéeke together. But thats but Fortune <hi>de la guerre,</hi> as the knaue of clubbes ſaid when he was baniſht the Towne, Wherefore to come to the purpoſe of my promiſe at our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (which was to ſend you ſuch newes as this Countrey brought forth) ſo it is that ſince the late battaile wee haue had nothing worth the noting, ſaue onely this, which is pleaſaunt to ſome, though irkeſome to others. At what time the king lay in leaguer of Paris againſt the daſtard traytor <hi>de Mayn,</hi> the ſaid recreant Duke had amongſt his holy orders two wel-fedde Friers, whereof the one was his baudy ghoſtly father, and principal confeſſor, the other was his chuffe-headed Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, and chiefe ſhaueling in ordinary. The firſt of them (whom they hight Frier <hi>Donnet</hi>) was in loue with a ſmugge faſt Nunne, about ſome ninetéene yeares of age, as good a wench as euer harde Maſſe at high midnight, which fat <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:11036:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
eſpying (for ſo was the younger called) began likewiſe to licke his lippes after her, and ſlauer out his loue in ſighs as well as he coulde, but ſéeing no way to compaſſe it, as long as his better was in place, and conſidering what infinite ſtore of Crownes olde <hi>Donnet</hi> coffered vppe by confeſſing in the time of the Pariſians diſtreſſe, and what credite he was in with the Duke, he caſt a thouſand plattes in his heade, how to diſplace him of all thrée at once, but none of them all woulde come off halfe roundly to his contentment a long time. In the end it ſo fell out that <hi>Mounſieur Scackerton</hi> to reuenge his fathers death, made a little breache into the Citty, and with ſome few of his followers ſlewe many of the League then faſt a ſléepe, in which confuſed conflict, there was ſuch a monſtruous hurly-burly in the Citty, that all the towne was in an vprore, and know not what ſhould become of them. Amongeſt them that feared moſt was this foreſaid Nun with breathleſſe <hi>Donnet,</hi> that had her in ſhrift betwixt the ſhéetes at the ſelfe ſame hour, which made the quaking Frier call to his fellowe <hi>Francis</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the next chamber, and aſked him what was the reaſon of that turmoile, who aunſwered he knew not as yet, but hee would goe and enquire, within halfe an houre after, hee came in blowing and puffing, and told him a long tale of a tubbe, how the King entring the Citty, was taken by a common ſouldiour, and preſented as priſoner to the Duke <hi>de Maine,</hi> as then in the market place. Now ſaies he brother <hi>Donnet</hi> if you will winne your ſpurs for euer, and behaue your ſelfe like a right man of God in déede, get you packing preſently to Rome, and be the firſt that ſhall tell his holineſſe of this good ſeruice, ſo ſhal you both come to excéeding promotion your ſelfe, and be able to pleaſure all your friends as you liſt. The rauiſht Frier ouerioyed with this oportunity, and gréedy of Honour and thankes which he hoped to reape by his meſſage, made no more adoe but reſigned his office, and ſiſter in bedde to Frier <hi>Francis</hi> both at once, ſaying if he neuer returned his was the gaine, for he knew by inſpiration, that great was the preferment which tended his newes. <hi>Francis</hi> excuſed himſelfe that the charge was ouermighty for him to go through with, and that there were many fitter men to vnder goe it then hee,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11036:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
yet thrice it had pleaſed him of his owne frée motion, to make <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of him before all other, he woulde endeuour to diſcharge it as well as he could. Many wordes of kindneſſe to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect paſt betwixt them, but the night farre ſpent and <hi>Donnet</hi> in haſt of his iourney, reacht his pigſney a dry kiſſe, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted through Aix, by ſhipping to <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heithen, and from thence tooke poſte to Rome, where he was no ſooner alighted, but he rouſed vp his reuerence, and new gla<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap> h<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> lippes with the lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, that he might kiſſe the Popes toe with commendation, wherein hée failed not a whitte, for méeting his holineſſe as he went to Sainct <hi>Peters</hi> to heare maſſe, he <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>kt downe ſo low as his garters would let him, and with a <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="5+ letters">
                  <desc>•••••…</desc>
               </gap>es mouth let flye at his ſlipper. Then began he with a <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="8+ letters">
                  <desc>〈8… letters〉</desc>
               </gap>es grace to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe the late conqueſt of Leaguer <hi>de Maine,</hi> againſt that Huguenot <hi>Henry</hi> of Burbon, who in a ſingle combate had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome him, and took him priſoner moſt brauely, to the great aduantage of the ſea Apoſtolicke, and vtter diſcom<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="6+ letters">
                  <desc>••••••…</desc>
               </gap> of all vſurping heretickes, amplifying by the way of an <gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onicall <hi>Proſopopeia,</hi> what deſpayring lamentations were made for him, by the Engliſh excommunicats, and the outlawes of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua, and in the Epilogue of his eloquence, her proteſted ſuch allegeance, as if he woulde diſpute with the deuill in defence of the papacy. The gorgeous controuler of Princes that al this while had attended his ſpeach, attracted ſuch inward ioy from this tale of ſucceſſe, that he commanded Maſſe to bée ſung in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery church, bone-fires to bée made in the ſtréetes, and a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne proceſſion to bée held throughout Rome, in which hée himſelfe marcht along to Sainct <hi>Angelos,</hi> vnder a rich cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſupported by foure Cardinals, ſprinkling the beholders with holy water all the way hee went. Neither was <hi>Donnet</hi> a ſmall property in this pageant, for hee had the bearing of the principalleſt Croſſe that day, allotted him in honor of his tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, whiles theſe things thus were a doing in Italy, the King entred battaile with <hi>de Maine,</hi> and by the won<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rful working of Heauen, (as it is not vnknowen in England) chaſed him the fielde, and made him retire for reſcue to <hi>Mentz,</hi> in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite of a common ſouldier, where it is ſaide hée tooke ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Through which accidentall miſhappe Frier <hi>Francis</hi> with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:11036:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
his Nunne now put to their ſhifts, and not hearing what was become of the Duke, determined to try the courteſie of other Countryes, ſince they found ſo little ſafety in their owne. But amorous <hi>Brigetta,</hi> that longed after the firſt cuſtomer, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded him to conuert his courſe vnto Rome, whereto he eaſely condiſcended. As they were thus on their way, the Duke <hi>du Maine,</hi> deſpairing in his auckward procéedings, and quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded in his forlorne cheualry, wrote lamentable letters to his holineſſe, by one <hi>Mounsier Belowe</hi> a frenche man, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he paſſionately reported his ill fortune, and diſmall diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, curſing the ſtarres that did boade him ſuch bitter miſhap, and the day that gaue light to that luckeleſſe diſgrace. Theſe letters came to the Pope in the middeſt of this triumphes and honors done to Frier <hi>Donnet,</hi> that now was in good hope to bée Cardinall. But he came ſhort of his longing, for when his beatitude beheld this balefull diſcourſe, and with throbbing heart had peruſed thoſe pitifull contents, hée called me his meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger in queſtion, who with trembling told him, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he had reported procéeded from one Frier <hi>Francis,</hi> that had thus informed him, and that he knewe of nothing but by him. By this time was the ſaide <hi>Francis</hi> with his Nunne come to Rome, and there thought to anchor ſecure from all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>combraunces of warre, but alacke for pitty, that might not be, his partner had eſpide him, and hée muſt needes come before the Pope, wher being examined vpon the cauſe and the Dukes letter ſhowne in the nicke, he was ſo confounded in his fiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, that ſtraight he confeſſed all the knauery, and appealed to the court for mercy. Yet notwithſtanding there conioyned ſubmiſſion, they were adiudged for penaunce of their preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to goe barefoote and barelegde through Rome, and whip eache other with whippes of wier vppe and downe the Citty, which the day following hée performed very faithfully. For Frier <hi>Donnet</hi> angerd at the heart at Frier <hi>Francis,</hi> to heare his treacherous conueyance about the Nunne, curſt him ſelfe a thouſand times that he had not a two hand whippe to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him, yet with that ſhort weapon that he had, hée belabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him indifferently, and <hi>Francis</hi> on the other ſide wounded him with his wiry waſters ſo wel fauoredly, that his back ſpat
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11036:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
bloud in his face at euery ſtripe he gaue him, who ſo hath ſéene two iackes in a clockhouſe ſtriking hie noone with their oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite hammers may well conceiue this anticke reſemblance. <hi>Donnet</hi> he behaued himſelfe like an old Fencer, that fetcheth his blow with a flouriſh, one while ſetting his right legge for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as though he lay at back-ſworde, he would ayme at a boane in ſtead of a button, anotherwhile framing his toe to the turne, he would bring his whippe about his head with a whiſke, and peirce through his thicke ſkinne coate into the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner regions of his ribbes. <hi>Francis</hi> thinking this was verie foule play to come behind a man and ſtrike him like a coward, and finding by proofe howe painefull it was to daunce to this thrée ſtringed muſicke, rayſed vp himſelfe on all tenne like a gander, and gaue him ſuch an item ouer the ſhoulders, that he had littie néede of any other Phlebothome in two monethes after, for it came ſo edglong, that it diſcarded all the ſkin from the necke to the middle, and put <hi>Donnet</hi> beſides his fence with the ſuddaine amazement, yet caſting his eies on his ſwéete Nun that went along by them he fell to it a freſh, &amp; made ſuch furrous in his fat brothers fleſh, as a man might haue ſéene through the fleſh to the bones: and he likewiſe layde ſuch load on my confeſſors curets, that he loſt aboue two laſh of wire in the loynes of his backe, whoſe rawbond ridges ſhewed in all pointes ſo like a redde lattice, that if a tincker had ſéene them he would vndoubtedly haue miſtooke him for an alehouſe. To be ſhort, in this mutuall combat continued they for the ſpace of thrée houres, till the wearineſſe of their ſtrength and extremi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of anguiſh, conſtrayned them to reſt. But ſo vnſpeakeable was their paine (as it is reported héere in <hi>Caen</hi>) that what with ſorrow for their fault, &amp; ſhame of their puniſhment they dyed within two daies after. Thus haue you heard in as briefe ſort as I could, the cometragicall hiſtorie of theſe vnfortunate Fryers, which is ſo laughed at here, and ſo much moned elſewhere. When I haue more newes I will ſend you more, in the meane time be merry with this, which I aſſure you for the ſubſtance of it is true, although it faile in ſome circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance, and ſo for this time I take my leaue, hoping to ſée you ere long in England.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From <hi>Caen</hi> in <hi>Normandie</hi>
               </dateline> by your friend. <signed>L. R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
